I'm speaking about compassion from an Islamic point of view,
انا اتحدث عن الشفقة والرحمة من وجهة نظر إسلامية ،
and perhaps my faith is not very well thought of
مع أن لا يعتقد الكثير من الناس
as being one that is grounded in compassion.
وجود علاقة وطيدة بين العقيدة الاسلامية و الرحمة
The truth of the matter is otherwise.
مع أن الحقيقة خلاف ذلك.
Our holy book, the Koran, consists of 114 chapters,
كتابنا المقدس القرآن الكريم ، يتألف من 114 سورة،
and each chapter begins with what we call the basmala,
وتبدأ كل سورة بما نسميه البسملة ،
the saying of "In the name of God, the all compassionate, the all merciful,"
قول بسم الله ، الرحمن الرحيم،
or, as Sir Richard Burton --
أو ، كما قال السيد ريتشارد بيرتون ،
not the Richard Burton who was married to Elizabeth Taylor,
ليس ريتشارد بيرتون الذي كان متزوجا من الممثلة الشهيرة اليزابيث تايلور ،
but the Sir Richard Burton who lived a century before that
بل السيد ريتشارد بيرتون الذي عاش قبل قرن من الزمان ذلك
and who was a worldwide traveler
والذي كان كان رحالة معروف
and translator of many works of literature --
و مترجم للعديد من الأعمال الأدبية
translates it. "In the name of God, the compassionating, the compassionate."
و ترجم:" بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم"
And in a saying of the Koran, which to Muslims is God speaking to humanity,
وذكر في القرآن الكريم ، الذي يعتبره المسلمون حديث الله الموجه للانسانية
God says to his prophet Muhammad --
أن الله بتكلم الى النبي محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم ،
whom we believe to be the last of a series of prophets,
و هو الذي نعتبره نحن المسلمون خاتمة الرسل و الأنبياء
beginning with Adam, including Noah, including Moses, including Abraham,
، ابتداءا بآدم مرورا بنوح و موسى و ابراهيم
including Jesus Christ, and ending with Muhammad --
وعيسى و انتهاءاً بمحمد
that, "We have not sent you, O Muhammad,
قال ان "وماأرسلناك يا محمد ،
except as a 'rahmah,' except as a source of compassion to humanity."
،وإلا رحمة للعالمين . "
For us human beings, and certainly for us as Muslims,
وبالنسبة لنا نحن البشر ، وبالتأكيد بالنسبة لنا كمسلمين ،
whose mission, and whose purpose in following the path of the prophet
و الذي نعتبرأن هدفنا هو اتباع منهج الرسول
is to make ourselves as much like the prophet.
بالتالي محاولة التشبه بالرسول و التحلي بصفاته.
And the prophet, in one of his sayings, said,
وقال ، النبي ، في واحدة من أقواله ،
"Adorn yourselves with the attributes of God."
"زينوا أنفسكم بصفات الله".
And because God Himself said that the primary attribute of his is compassion --
ولأن الله نفسه قال إن السمة الأساسية له هو الرحمة ،
in fact, the Koran says that "God decreed upon himself compassion,"
في الواقع ، يقول القرآن ان "حكم الله على نفسه بالرحمة"،
or, "reigned himself in by compassion" --
أو "في حكم نفسه بالعطف".
therefore, our objective and our mission must be to be sources of compassion,
ولذلك ، يجب أن يكون هدفنا ومهمتناأن نكون من مصادر الرحمة ،
activators of compassion, actors of compassion
، مفعلين و محدثين للرحمة،
and speakers of compassion and doers of compassion.
متحدثين عن الرحمة و فاعلين للرحمة،
That is all well and good,
كل ذلك حسنا وجيدا ،
but where do we go wrong,
ولكن أين أخطأنا ،
and what is the source of the lack of compassion in the world?
و ماهو سبب قلة الرحمة في العالم؟
For the answer to this, we turn to our spiritual path.
من أجل الإجابة على هذا ،نرجع الى منهجنا الروحي.
In every religious tradition, there is the outer path and the inner path,
في كل التقاليد الدينية هناك ما تسمونه المسار الخارجي والمسار الداخلي ،
or the exoteric path and the esoteric path.
أو المسار الظاهر والمسار المقصور على فئة معينة.
The esoteric path of Islam is more popularly known as Sufism, or "tasawwuf" in Arabic.
المسار الباطني للإسلام هو أكثر معرفة بالصوفية أو التصوف في اللغة العربية.
And these doctors or these masters,
وهؤلاء الأطباء أو هؤلاء السادة ،
these spiritual masters of the Sufi tradition,
هؤلاء المعلمون الروحانيون للتقاليد الصوفية ،
refer to teachings and examples of our prophet
يرجون إلى دروس و أمثال من الرسول
that teach us where the source of our problems lies.
و التي تدلنا على مصدر مشاكلنا
In one of the battles that the prophet waged,
في واحدة من المعارك التي شنها النبي ،
he told his followers, "We are returning from the lesser war
وقال لأتباعه ، وقال "اننا عائدون من الجهادالأصغر
to the greater war, to the greater battle."
لمزيد من الحرب ، إلى الجهاد أكبر ".
And they said, "Messenger of God, we are battle-weary.
وقالوا : "رسول الله ، ونحن الذين انهكتهم الحرب.
How can we go to a greater battle?"
كيف يمكن لنا أن نذهب إلى جهاد أكبر؟ "
He said, "That is the battle of the self, the battle of the ego."
وقال : "هذه هي جهاد المصير ، جهاد النفس".
The sources of human problems have to do with egotism, "I."
و تكون مشاكل الإنسان لها علاقة مع الأنانية ،الأنا.
The famous Sufi master Rumi, who is very well known to most of you,
للسيد جلال الدين الرومي الصوفي الشهير ، الذي هو معروف جيدا لمعظمكم ،
has a story in which he talks of a man who goes to the house of a friend,
يتحدث عن قصة لديه عن رجل يذهب الى منزل صديق
and he knocks on the door,
ويطرق على الباب ،
and a voice answers, "Who's there?"
و يجيبه صوت ، و"من هناك؟"
"It's me," or, more grammatically correctly, "It is I,"
"إنه أنا" ، أو أكثر بشكل سليم نحويا "، وهو الأنا ،"
as we might say in English.
كما يمكننا أن نقول إن في اللغة الإنجليزية.
The voice says, "Go away."
صوت يقول : "اذهب بعيدا".
After many years of training, of disciplining, of search and struggle,
بعد سنوات عديدة من التدريب ، التأديب ، البحث والنضال ،
he comes back.
رجع ،
With much greater humility, he knocks again on the door.
وبقدر أكبر من التواضع ، يقرع على الباب مرة أخرى.
The voice asks, "Who is there?"
صوت يتساءل "من هناك؟"
He said, "It is you, O heartbreaker."
وقال : "إنه أنت ، يا القلب المنكسر ".
The door swings open, and the voice says,
يتأرجح الباب مفتوحا ، وصوت يقول :
"Come in, for there is no room in this house for two I's,"
ادخل ، لأنه لا يكون مجال في هذا المنزل لإثنين من "الأنا" ،
-- two capital I's, not these eyes -- "for two egos."
أعني بها "الأنا: الذات" ، وليست "العيون" ، لاثنين من الغرور.
And Rumi's stories are metaphors for the spiritual path.
وجلال الدين الرومي قصص هي مجازات للمنهج الروحي.
In the presence of God, there is no room for more than one "I,"
في وجود الله، لايوجد مجال لأكثر من "أنا" واحدة
and that is the "I" of divinity.
وهذا هو الأنا(النفس) من الألوهية.
In a teaching -- called a "hadith qudsi" in our tradition --
في التدريس ، ويسمى الحديث القدسي في تقاليدنا ،
God says that, "My servant," or "My creature, my human creature,
يقول الله تعالى أن "عبدي" ، أو "مخلوقي ،مخلوقي البشري،
does not approach me by anything that is dearer to me
لا شيء يقربك إلي أحب إلي
than what I have asked them to do."
مما قد طلبت منهم ان يفعلوه. "
And those of you who are employers know exactly what I mean.
ويعرف أرباب العمل الذين هم أولئك منكم تماما ما أعنيه.
You want your employees to do what you ask them to do,
موظفيك تريد أن تفعل ما كنت أطلب منهم أن يفعلوا ،
and if they've done that, then they can do extra.
و ان أكملوه تطلبون منهم عمل المزيد
But don't ignore what you've asked them to do.
ولكن لا تتجاهل ما كنت قد طلبت منهم أن يفعلوا.
"And," God says, "my servant continues to get nearer to me,
والله يقول : "لا يزال عبدي يتقرب لي ،
by doing more of what I've asked them to do" --
عن طريق القيام بالمزيد من ما كنت طلبت منهم ان يفعلوا "
extra credit, we might call it --
رصيد إضافي ، قد نسميها ،
"until I love him or love her.
"حتى أحبه أو أحبها.
And when I love my servant," God says,
وعندما أحب عبدي "، يقول الله تعالى ،
"I become the eyes by which he or she sees,
أصبحت العيون الذي أو التي ترى بهما ،
the ears by which he or she listens,
الآذنان الذي هو أو هي تستمع بهما،
the hand by which he or she grasps,
يداه التي يبطش به أو بها،
and the foot by which he or she walks,
وقدماه التي يمشي أو تمشي بها ،
and the heart by which he or she understands."
وقلبه الذي أو التي تفهم به ".
It is this merging of our self with divinity
هذا هو دمج جهودنا الذاتية مع الألوهية
that is the lesson and purpose of our spiritual path and all of our faith traditions.
هذا هو الدرس المستفاد والغرض من طريقنا الروحي وجميع شركائنا في التقاليد الدينية.
Muslims regard Jesus as the master of Sufism,
يعتبر المسلمون يسوع هو سيد الصوفية ،
the greatest prophet and messenger who came to emphasize the spiritual path.
الرسول الأعظم والرسول الذي جاء للتأكيدعلى المنهج الروحي
When he says, "I am the spirit, and I am the way,"
عندما يقول : "أنا الروح ، وأنا هو الطريق"
and when the prophet Muhammad said, "Whoever has seen me has seen God,"
عندما النبي محمد قال : "من رآني فقد شهد الله" ،
it is because they became so much an instrument of God,
فذلك لأنهم أصبحوا أداة لله ،
they became part of God's team --
أنها أصبحوا جزءا من قوة الله ،
so that God's will was manifest through them,
ذلك ان ارادة الله كانت قائمة من خلالهم
and they were not acting from their own selves and their own egos.
وأنه لا يعمل من أجل مصلحتهم الذاتية وأناتهم الخاصة.
Compassion on earth is given, it is in us.
الرحمة على الأرض موجودة، و موجودة فينا،
All we have to do is to get our egos out of the way,
كل ما علينا عمله هو أن نزيح كبريائنامن الطريق.
get our egotism out of the way.
الأنانية من الطريق
I'm sure, probably all of you here, or certainly the very vast majority of you,
أنا متأكد ، وربما كل واحد منكم هنا ، أو من المؤكد أن الغالبية الساحقة جدا منكم ،
have had what you might call a spiritual experience,
كان لها ما يمكن أن نسميه تجربة روحية ،
a moment in your lives when, for a few seconds, a minute perhaps,
لحظة في حياتكم ، لبضع ثوان ، وربما لمدة دقيقة ،
the boundaries of your ego dissolved.
تلاشت حدود ذاتك.
And at that minute, you felt at one with the universe --
و في تلك اللحظة أحسستم باتحاد مع الكون ،
one with that jug of water, one with every human being,
باتحاد مع إبريق ماء ، باتحاد مع كل كائن بشري ،
one with the Creator --
واحدة مع الخالق ،
and you felt you were in the presence of power, of awe,
و أحسستم بوجود القوة ،والرعب ،
of the deepest love, the deepest sense of compassion and mercy
و أحسسستم بقوة الحب و الرحمة
that you have ever experienced in your lives.
التي لم تعيشوا مثلها من قبل في حياتكم
That is a moment which is a gift of God to us --
هذه هي اللحظة التي هي هبة من الله لنا ،
a gift when, for a moment, he lifts that boundary
هدية ،في تلك اللحظةحين ترفع الحدود
which makes us insist on "I, I, I, me, me, me,"
التي تجعلنا نصر و نتشبث بالأنا و الكبرياء باستمرار
and instead, like the person in Rumi's story,
وبدلا من ذلك ، مثل هذا الشخص في قصة جلال الدين الرومي ،
we say, "Oh, this is all you.
نقول : "أوه ، هذا هو كل شيء لك."
This is all you. And this is all us.
هذا هو كل شيء لك. وهذا هو كل شيء لنا.
And us, and I, and us are all part of you.
ولنا ، وأنا ، ونحن جميعا جزء من أنت.
O, Creator! O, the Objective! The source of our being
كل مبدع ، كل الهدف ، مصدر وجودنا ،
and the end of our journey,
ونهاية رحلتنا.
you are also the breaker of our hearts.
انت ايضا الموجة من قلوبنا.
You are the one whom we should all be towards, for whose purpose we live,
أنت الواحد الذي يجب علينا جميعا أن نكون صوبه ، الغرض الذي نعيش فيه ،
and for whose purpose we shall die,
والغرض الذي يجب أن نموت عليه ،
and for whose purpose we shall be resurrected again
و نبعث مرة أخرى
to account to God to what extent we have been compassionate beings."
ليحاسبنا الله على مدى رحمتنا
Our message today, and our purpose today,
رسالتنا اليوم ، وهدفنا اليوم ،
and those of you who are here today,
وأولئك منكم الذين نجتمع هنا اليوم ،
and the purpose of this charter of compassion, is to remind.
والغرض من هذا الميثاق من الرحمة ،
For the Koran always urges us to remember, to remind each other,
هو لتذكيرنا بأن القرآن يحثنا دائما بأن نتذكر و نذكر بعضنا
because the knowledge of truth is within every human being.
لأن معرفة الحقيقة هي داخل كل إنسان.
We know it all.
و نحن نعلمها كلها
We have access to it all.
، و لدينا مدخل لها
Jung may have called it "the subconscious."
قد دعاها "جونغ" بالعقل الباطن
Through our subconscious, in your dreams --
خلال عقلنا الباطن،و خلال أحلامكم،
the Koran calls our state of sleep "the lesser death,"
القرآن يطلق على حالة نومنا : "النوم الأصغر ، أو النوم المؤقت"
"the temporary death" --
الموت المؤقت.
in our state of sleep we have dreams, we have visions,
عندما نكون نيام تراودنا الأحلام، لدينا رؤى،
we travel even outside of our bodies, for many of us,
نسافر حتى خارج أجسامنا،
and we see wonderful things.
و نرى أشياء رائعة،
We travel beyond the limitations of space as we know it,
نحن نسافر ما وراء حدود الفضاء كما نعرفها،
and beyond the limitations of time as we know it.
وما وراء حدود الزمن كما نعرفه.
But all this is for us to glorify the name of the creator
ولكن كل هذا هو بالنسبة لنا لتمجيد اسم الخالق
whose primary name is the compassionating, the compassionate.
واسمه الأول هو الرحمن الرحيم.
God, Bokh, whatever name you want to call him with, Allah, Ram, Om,
إله ،بوخ،أيا كان الاسم الذي تريد الاتصال به مع ، الله ، رام ، أم ،
whatever the name might be through which you name
أيا كان الاسم الذي تودون الطلاقه عليه
or access the presence of divinity,
أيا كان هذا الاسم الذي تطلقونه على أساس الخلود،
it is the locus of absolute being,
هو منبع الوجود المطلق،
absolute love and mercy and compassion,
الحب و الرحمة المطلقة،
and absolute knowledge and wisdom,
والمعرفة والحكمة المطلقة ،
what Hindus call "satchidananda."
ما يسمونه الهندوس ستشيداناندا .
The language differs,
تختلف اللغة ،
but the objective is the same.
ولكن الهدف هو نفسه.
Rumi has another story
لدى جلال الدين الرومي قصة أخرى
about three men, a Turk, an Arab and --
تدور حول ثلاثة رجال من أجناس مختلفة: تركي ، عربي ،
and I forget the third person, but for my sake, it could be a Malay.
عربي و .. نسيت الشخص الثالث و لكن أظن أنه "مالاي"
One is asking for angur -- one is, say, an Englishman --
واحد يسأل عن "أنغور" :" عنب بالتركية"
one is asking for eneb, and one is asking for grapes.
واحد يسأل عن عنب" باللغة العربية"، و الثالث يسأل عن العنب" باللغة الانجليزية.
And they have a fight and an argument because
و حدثت بينهم مشادة حول ذلك،
-- "I want grapes." "I want eneb. "I want angur." --
أريد العنب ، وأنا أريد "إنب" ، أريد "أنغور" ،
not knowing that the word that they're using
ظنا منهم أنهم يريدون أشياء مختلفة
refers to the same reality in different languages.
دون أن يعلموا أنهم كلهم يريدون الشئ نفسهو نفس الواقع،بلغات مختلفة
There's only one absolute reality by definition,
و هناك حقيقة واحدة فقط ،
one absolute being by definition,
كيان مطلق واحد،
because absolute is, by definition, single,
لأن المطلق هو ، بحكم التعريف ، واحد ،
and absolute and singular.
والمطلق والمفرد.
There's this absolute concentration of being,
يكون هناك يجري هذا التركيز المطلق ،
the absolute concentration of consciousness,
التركيز المطلق للوعي ،
awareness, an absolute locus of compassion and love
الوعي ، المنبع المطلق للرحمة و الحب
that defines the primary attributes of divinity.
الذي يعرفنا بالسمات الأساسية للخلود
And these should also be
وأنه ينبغي أيضا أن تكون
the primary attributes of what it means to be human.
السمات الأساسية لما يعنيه أن يكون الانسان إنسانا.
For what defines humanity, perhaps biologically,
لتعريف الانسانية، ربما من ناحية بيولوجية،
is our physiology,
لدينا علم وظائف الأعضاء ،
but God defines humanity by our spirituality, by our nature.
ولكن الله يعرف الإنسانية من قيمنا الروحية ، من طبيعتنا.
And the Koran says, He speaks to the angels and says,
ويقول القرآن ، وقال انه يتحدث الى الملائكة ، ويقول :
"When I have finished the formation of Adam from clay,
وقال "عندما تم الانتهاء من تشكيل آدم من طين ،
and breathed into him of my spirit,
ونفخت فيه من روحي ،
then, fall in prostration to him."
ثم تقع في السجود له ".
The angels prostrate, not before the human body,
و سجدت الملائكة ، ليس لجسم الإنسان ،
but before the human soul.
ولكن للنفس البشرية.
Why? Because the soul, the human soul,
لماذا؟ لأن الروح والنفس البشرية ،
embodies a piece of the divine breath,
يجسد قطعة من النفس الالهية ،
a piece of the divine soul.
قطعة من الروح الإلهية.
This is also expressed in biblical vocabulary
وأعرب أيضا عن هذا في الكتاب المقدس المفردات
when we are taught that we were created in the divine image.
عندما ونحن على علم بأننا كنا خلق على صورة الله.
What is the imagery of God?
ما هي الصور الملتقطة من الله؟
The imagery of God is absolute being,
هي الكيان المطلق
absolute awareness and knowledge and wisdom
الوعي المطلق والمعرفة والحكمة
and absolute compassion and love.
والرحمة والحب المطلق.
And therefore, for us to be human --
بالتالي أن نكون بشر،
in the greatest sense of what it means to be human,
بمعنى أعظم ما يعنيه أن نكون يشر ،
in the most joyful sense of what it means to be human --
بمعنى أكثر المبتهجين في ما يعنيه أن يكون الإنسان ،
means that we too have to be proper stewards
يعني أننا أيضاأنع يتعين علينا أن نكون مضيفين جيدين للروح الخالدة داخلنا،
of the breath of divinity within us,
من التنفس من الألوهية في داخلنا ،
and seek to perfect within ourselves the attribute of being,
والسعي إلى الكمال داخل أنفسنا،
of being alive, of beingness;
يمة أن نكون على قيد الحياة ،
the attribute of wisdom, of consciousness, of awareness;
السمة من الحكمة والوعي ،
and the attribute of being compassionate and loving beings.
والسمة من الرحمة والشفقة والمحبة البشر.
This is what I understand from my faith tradition,
هذا ما أفهمه من عادات عقيدتي
and this is what I understand from my studies of other faith traditions,
وهذا هو ما أفهمه من دراستي للتقاليد الدينية الأخرى ،
and this is the common platform on which we must all stand,
وهذا هو المنصة المشتركة التي يجب أن نقف عليها جميعا،
and when we stand on this platform as such,
وعندما نقف على هذا المنبر على هذا النحو ،
I am convinced that we can make a wonderful world.
فانني مقتنع أننا نستطيع أن نخلق عالما رائعا
And I believe, personally, that we're on the verge
وأعتقد ، شخصيا ، وأننا على وشك ،
and that, with the presence and help of people like you here,
وأنه مع وجود ومساعدة من أشخاص مثلكم هنا ،
we can bring about the prophecy of Isaiah.
يمكننا تحقيق نبوءة إسياه.
For he foretold of a period
لكنه تنبأ لفترة
when people shall transform their swords into plowshares
عندما كان الناس يحولون سيوفهم سككا
and will not learn war or make war anymore.
ولن يتعلموا الحرب ويشنواالحروب بعد الآن.
We have reached a stage in human history that we have no option:
اننا وصلنا الى مرحلة في التاريخ البشري ، وأنه ليس لدينا خيار.
we must, we must lower our egos,
يجب علينا ، يجب علينا أن نقلل من الغرور ،
control our egos -- whether it is individual ego, personal ego,
نسيطر على الغرور ، سواء كانت الأنا فردية ، والأنا الشخصية ،
family ego, national ego --
والأنا الأسرية و الأنا الوطنية ،
and let all be for the glorification of the one.
والسماح للجميع لتمجيد الواحد.
Thank you, and God bless you.
شكرا لكم ، وبارك الله فيكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق).